Guide to the World Student Christian Federation North America Regional Office Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
World Student Christian Federation North America Regional Office Records
1920-2010
1973-1989
RG 46A
Yale University Divinity School Library
15
(34 boxes)
This record group documents the operations of the North America Regional Office of the WSCF and the issues that were of concern to the Office. The records complement Record Group 46, Archives of the World Student Christian Federation, which documents the activities of the WSCF and WSCF-related student Christian movements around the world from 1875 to 1972. The North America Regional Office of the World Student Christian Federation existed from 1973 to 1988. Its purpose was to coordinate ecumenical Christian student work in the U. S. and Canada.
World Student Christian Federation
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the WSCF North America Regional Office.
Biographical / Historical
The North America Regional Office of the World Student Christian Federation was formed in 1973. Six WSCF Regional Offices (Africa, Asia/Pacific, Europe, Latin America, Middle East and North America) were created at this time to serve as governing bodies for the student Christian movements. The Regional Offices were in turn coordinated by the WSCF Inter-Regional Office (IRO) in Geneva, the central administrative body of the WSCF.
Within the North America Region, the North America Regional Committee (NARC) made official decisions regarding policy, program and budget. This Committee was composed of eight delegates, four from the Student Christian Movement of Canada (SCM-Canada) and four from the United States, the majority of whom were students. It met every 12 to 18 months.
The North America Regional Executive Committee was comprised of a smaller group of four delegates (two from Canada, two from the U.S.), elected by the NARC. This group met monthly, in conjunction with the North America Regional Office staff, to conduct the business of the Region between NARC meetings.
According to the structure of the WSCF, one student Christian movement in each country can be considered for "affiliated" status with the WSCF. Affiliated movements are to be national, ecumenical and student-run, with more than one active local unit. Affiliated status is conferred at the quadrennial meetings of the WSCF General Assembly upon the recommendation of the Regional Committees. Affiliated movements are entitled to one voting delegate at the General Assembly. In the North America Region, the affiliated movement for Canada has been the Student Christian Movement of Canada.*( Documentation is available in this collection for movements indicated with an "*".) The SCM-Canada was founded in 1922 and continues to exist. The designation of one student Christian movement in the United States as an affiliated movement of the WSCF has been problematic. The University Christian Movement had affiliated status until it disbanded in 1969. Twelve years later in 1981, the National Ecumenical Student Christian Council of the U.S. (NESCC) was formed. It applied for affiliated status with the WSCF, which was conferred upon it at the 1986 General Assembly. However, at the same General Assembly, the NESCC disbanded. Since that time, there has been no national ecumenical student Christian movement in the United States.
Regional Committees can grant "associated" status to movements which do not meet all the criteria for affiliation (i.e. are not national, ecumenical and student-run). Associated movements are allowed to send a representative to the General Assembly who can speak and make proposals, but not vote. The associated movements in the North America Region included the Association of Christian Student Leaders (ACSL), California Student Christian Movement*, Lutheran Student Movement in the U.S.A.* and Canada*, the National Student YWCA and the University Christian Movement in New England*.
The North America Region was under the leadership of several regional secretaries during its 15-year period of operation. Placide Bazoche and Jan Griesinger were appointed by the IRO in 1973. The NARC selected successors Peter Johnson and Judy Skinner in 1975, Inge Thierauf and John Boonstra in April 1978, Debra House in September 1978, Gary Whynacht in 1980 and John O'Brien in 1984. The position brought many challenges, requiring frequent traveling, planning for and attendance at many meetings and conferences, and continuous communication with regional and inter-regional staff members.
The demands of dealing with such a varied constituency of persons, movements, organizations, issues and goals making up the Federation led to a shortened tenure for some staff members. Peter Johnson left his position in 1978. Inge Thierauf was released from her duties as Regional Co-Secretary in September 1978, followed by John Boonstra and Debra House in 1980. Their releases resulted in some controversy among North American staff members. Gary Whynacht resigned in 1983. John O'Brien's term of office ended with his death in 1988.
Staff changes and structural inadequacies in the North America Region slowly took their toll on the movement. The changing needs of their constituency in the late 1980s required structural adaptations which the North America Region was not prepared to make. The collapse of the NESCC and the disbanding of the NARC significantly affected the Region. United States and Canadian movements decided that the changing needs of Christian students must be met through more creative structures and programs. Thus, the WSCF North America Regional Office, as it had existed, had become obsolete.
In July, 1988, the IRO officially announced the closing of the North America Regional Office.(See the IRO's letter dated July, 1988 announcing the dissolution of the North America Regional Office. Series II, Box 7, Folder 129A) The Region's administrative affairs were absorbed by the IRO and unspent funds were used for travel and projects in North America and other regions.
Scope and Contents
I. North America Committee Records
II. North America Regional Office Operations
III. WSCF Inter-Regional Office and Regional Offices
IV. Related Ecumenical Student Movements
V. Related Organizations
VI. Addendum
The records document the activities of the North America Regional Office of the World Student Christian Federation during its fifteen-year period of operation, 1973 through 1988. The collection focuses primarily on the North American Office and student movements in the United States and Canada, but includes some material relating to other WSCF Regional Offices and related organizations. The records in this group are an addendum to Record Group 46, Archives of the World Student Christian Federation, which documents the activities of the WSCF and WSCF-related student Christian movements around the world from 1875 to 1972. The official archives of the WSCF, dating 1925 to the present, are located at the organization's headquarters in Geneva, Switzerland.
Series I contains records of the major decision-making bodies of the North America Region: the North America Regional Committee (NARC), the Canadian "affiliated" movement (SCM-Canada), various national U.S. committees, and the North American Trustees of the WSCF. These committees sometimes met jointly under the North America Regional Committee, but frequently held separate meetings to discuss more specific issues. These records document the Region's policies and programs as well as changes in NARC staff and structure. The materials include reports, minutes, meeting agenda, by-laws and constitutions, dating from 1973 through 1987.
Some materials from the Geneva office of the WSCF are included in Series I. Reports include activities of the North America region, and other materials were collected by North America staff members who attended Geneva meetings. Other documents include papers and reports presented by the North America staff to the Geneva office.
Series II documents the daily activities of the North America Regional Office and its staff. These office files provide insight into the duties of the Regional Secretaries and reflect their specific activities and concerns. Correspondence details the interactions of the office staff with each other, with staff from the Inter-Regional and other Regional Offices, and with related movements and organizations. Of particular interest in Series II is material relating to the planning and execution of the many conferences, programs, workshops and projects sponsored by the Regional Office. Conference themes reflected issues of interest and importance to Christians in North America during the period, particularly political, social and moral concerns. Such issues included political unrest in other regions, labor unions in Canada, women's roles in the church and society, and homosexuality.
Series III contains material pertaining to the operations of the Geneva office of the WSCF and of the Regional Offices other than the North America Office. These materials were collected by the North America Regional Office staff through communications with the Geneva and Regional Offices and through participation in their committee meetings, conferences and other activities.
The Geneva office papers include material pertaining to the Inter-Regional Office, WSCF Executive Committee, General Assembly and Universal Day of Prayer for Students. Also included are materials from the Africa, Asia/Pacific, Europe, Latin America and Middle East Regional Offices.
Regional material in Series III is valuable for the insight it provides into the difficulties of Christian activities in war-torn countries and politically-repressed societies. The collection is particularly rich in material on Nicaragua, with accounts of daily life as seen by WSCF visitors. There is documentation on the arrests and torture of Asians. Material pertaining to Africa reveals the region's social situation in the 1980s, focusing on such issues as apartheid, poverty and church work.
Series IV, Related Ecumenical Student Movements, is comprised of material from student Christian movements which share the same focus and goals as the World Student Christian Federation. Several movements in this series are officially associated with the WSCF, including the California Student Christian Movement, Lutheran Student Movement of the U.S.A and Canada, and the University Christian Movement in New England. These movements are filed among the papers from other related movements in the collection. The lack of a complete, current list of associated movements prevented the identification of other movements' official relationships to the WSCF.
Series V contains material from various religious organizations which was collected by the North America Regional Committee staff. The reasons for their collecting this material are varied and, sometimes, unclear. Some organizations sponsored joint conferences or programs with the NARC. NARC staff attended other independently-sponsored events. The NARC apparently acquired other materials by being on these organizations mailing lists.
Denominational organizations such as the United Methodist Church and the Lutheran Student Movement (a movement officially associated with the WSCF) are also included in Series V. Of particular note are the Frontier Internship in Mission and Young Christians for Global Justice, in which the NARC actively participated.
Overall, the collection provides insight into the challenges of student Christian work throughout the decades of the 1970s and 1980s. The management styles of the regional secretaries contrasts greatly with that of the WSCF leaders in Record Group No. 46. The material reflects a more casual style of interaction among staff members. Any gaps in correspondence can be attributed to the wide use of telephone communication. The papers reflect a willingness among the regional movements to adapt to social change. Their desire to uphold a Federation which did not discriminate on the basis of race, gender or sexual preference is evident, as is their continued status as an ecumenical movement.
Arrangement
I. North America Committee Records
II. North America Regional Office Operations
III. WSCF Inter-Regional Office and Regional Offices
IV. Related Ecumenical Student Movements
V. Related Organizations
VI. Addendum
Ecumenical movement; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Canada -- Religion; United States -- Religion; Bazoche, Placide; Boonstra, John; Griesinger, Jan; House, Debra; Johnson, Peter; O'Brien, John; Skinner, Judy; Thierauf, Inge; Whynacht, Gary; California Student Christian Movement; Lutheran Student Movement in Canada; Lutheran Student Movement--USA; Student Christian Movement of Canada; University Christian Movement in New England; World Student Christian Federation
- North America Committee Records, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is divided into six chronologically arranged sections:
  1. North America Regional Committee (NARC)
  2. Student Christian Movement of Canada (SCM-Canada)
  3. U.S. (Advisory) Committee
  4. U.S. Church Relations Committee
  5. U.S. Church Relations Task Group
  6. Trustees of the WSCF
  - North America Regional Committee (NARC)
    - NARC Meeting - Barrington, Illinois (minutes), 1973 Oct 19-21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - NARC Meeting - Winnipeg, Manitoba (preparatory materials, minutes), 1974 Jun 21-23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - NARC Meeting - Strangewood, King City, Ontario (by-laws, minutes), 1975 Nov 21-23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - NARC Meeting - Strangewood, King City, Ontario (minutes, documents), 1976 Nov 12-14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - North American Region Report to WSCF General Assembly, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - NARC Meeting - Toronto, Ontario (agenda, reports, minutes), 1977 Nov 11-13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - North American Region Program, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - NARC Executive Committee meeting - Toronto, 1978 Jun 25-27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Outline for Evaluation of Meetings (proposed at WSCF International Executive Committee meeting, Nairobi, Kenya), 1978 Jul (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - NARC Meeting - Toronto, Ontario, 1978 Sep 22-24 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
    - NARC Meetings - miscellaneous (bound volume of minutes reports), 1978 Oct-1979 Mar (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - NARC Meeting - Toronto, Ontario (preparatory documents, travel logistics), 1978 Nov 10-12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Assessment of the Role of Women in the Federation (response to questionnaire), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Goals and Methods for Work in Canada, 1979 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - NARC Executive Committee meeting - Toronto, 1979 Sep 22-23 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Booklet of Minutes Reports (including NARC, U.S. Committee and Canadian Caucus meetings), 1979 Oct-Nov (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - NARC Meeting - Toronto, Ontario (preparatory materials, change of by-laws), 1979 Nov 9-11 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - WSCF (incl. NARC) Programme, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - NARC Executive Committee meeting (minutes), 1980 Feb 8-10 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - NARC Annual Report, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - NARC Meeting - Toronto, Ontario (preparatory materials), 1981 Mar 20-22 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Constitution of the WSCF (adopted at the Executive Committee meeting, Berkeley, California), 1981 Aug (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - NARC Executive Committee meeting (working documents of Gary Whynacht), 1981 Nov 28-30 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - NARC Executive Committee meeting - Toronto (minutes), 1982 Jan 29-31 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - NARC By-laws Definitions, 1982 Oct (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - NARC Meeting - Toronto, Ontario (preparatory material, agenda, planning, minutes), 1982 Oct 15-17 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
    - NARC Executive Committee meeting - Toronto (minutes), 1983 Oct 23-25 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - WSCF Interim Committee meeting - Geneva (minutes), 1983 Nov 14-18 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - North America Region Annual Report, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - NARC Executive Committee meeting - New York City (minutes), 1984 May 11-13 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Selection of John O'Brien as WSCF-NA Regional Secretary, 1984 Jul (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - NARC Meeting - Toronto, Ontario (preparatory materials, minutes), 1984 Sep 20-23 (Box 2, Folder 37-39)
    - NARC Meeting - New York City (agenda, preparatory materials, enclosures for minutes from Fiona Brownlee), 1985 May 22-26 (Box 2, Folder 40-42)
    - (notes, drafts, minutes) (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
    - National Caucus Reports, 1985 May 23 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - NARC Priorities Paper - "Priorities of the North American Region of the WSCF", 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - NARC Quadrennial Report Assessment, 1981 Aug-1985 Sep (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - NARC Meeting - Mexico City, Mexico (preparatory materials, minutes), 1986 Mar 5-7 (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
    - NARC Annual Report, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - NARC - Miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Student Christian Movement of Canada (SCM-Canada)
    - Historical papers: "The Role of Theology and Politics in the SCM", 1920s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - National Council meeting (report), 1973 May (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - National Council meeting - Lunenburg County, Nova Scotia (minutes), 1977 Aug 28-31 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Board of Directors meeting - Kingston, Ontario (minutes, packet from problem-solving sessions attended by board members), 1978 Feb 24-26 (Box 3, Folder 55-56)
    - "Fundraising Hints" booklet, 1978 Jun (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - National Council meeting - Vancouver, B.C. (minutes), 1978 Aug 27-Sep 2 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Board of Directors meeting - Toronto, Ontario (minutes, reports, misc. papers), 1979 Mar 2-4 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - National Council meeting - Portland, Ontario (minutes, documents), 1979 Aug 28-Sep 2 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Regional Co-Secretary Report (Debra House) - Brief to Legislature re. Equal Value Legislation, 1980 Jan 16 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Regional Co-Secretary Report (Debra House) - Brief to Legislature re. Emergency Powers Legislation, 1980 Feb 5 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Board of Directors meeting (reports, documents), 1980 Feb 15-18 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - National Board meeting (report), 1980 Feb 18 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - National Council meeting - University of British Columbia (minutes), 1981 Sep 2-6 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Executive Committee meeting - Toronto (minutes), 1981 Nov 20-22 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - National Council meeting - Winnipeg, Manitoba, 1982 Aug 30-Sep 4 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Board of Directors Central Committee - Toronto, Ontario, 1984 Jan 17-22 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Executive Committee meeting, 1984 Mar 2-4 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - National Council meeting - Winnipeg, Manitoba (minutes, preparatory package), 1984 Aug 24-Sep 2 (Box 4, Folder 70-71)
    - Board of Directors meeting - Toronto (minutes), 1985 May 16-19 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Basis and Aims, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Advisory Board meeting (agenda), 1986 Jan 21 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Steering Committee meeting - Ontario (minutes), 1986 May 24-25 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Board of Directors - Toronto, Ontario (reports, documents), 1987 Sep 24-26 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - U.S. (Advisory) Committee
    - Meeting - Packard Manse, Stoughton, 1973 Mar 10-11 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Meeting - Barrington, Illinois, 1973 Oct 17-18 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Meeting - Berkeley, California, 1974 Mar 29-31 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Meeting - Atlanta, Georgia, 1974 Nov 15-17 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Meeting - Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1975 Oct 24-26 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Meeting - Knoxville, Tennessee, 1976 Oct 15-17 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Theological Convocation - Chicago, Illinois (report), 1977 Apr 2-3 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Meeting - Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1977 Oct 21-23 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Meeting - Madison, Wisconsin, 1978 Oct 20-22 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Meeting - Ithaca, New York, 1979 Apr 20-22 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Meeting - Berkeley, California, 1979 Oct 12-14 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Meeting - Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1980 Apr 18-20 (Box 5, Folder 89-90)
    - Meeting - New York City, 1980 Nov 14-16 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Meeting - St. Paul, Minnesota, 1982 Apr 2-4 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - U.S. Church Relations Committee
    - Proposal for 1978 program support, 1977 Jun 10 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Reports, minutes, agenda, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 94-96)
    - Communications, memos, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Reports, minutes, agenda, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 98-99)
    - Reports, minutes, agenda, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Mailing lists, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - U.S. Church Relations Task Group
    - Materials, correspondence, 1984 Oct-1985 Oct (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Minutes of meeting, 1985 Feb 22 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Meeting agenda, materials, 1985 Aug 29 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Trustees of the WSCF
    - Reports, minutes, agenda (incl. Church Relations Trust Committee), 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - re. General Assembly, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Minutes, reports, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 107)
- North American Regional Office Operations, Series II
  This Series is divided into seven sections as follows:
  1. Secretaries' Files/Correspondence
  2. Staff
  3. Conferences, Programs, Workshops
  4. Projects
  5. Financial Records
  6. Publications
  7. Photographs
  The Secretaries' Files are arranged alphabetically by the individual or organization with which the WSCF-NA Regional Secretaries corresponded. Material pertaining to staff members includes job descriptions and documentation of travel. Special projects and conferences sponsored by the North American Region are arranged chronologically. Financial records, in chronological sequence, include budget, funding and grants. Publications of the North American Region are listed alphabetically.
  - Secretaries' Files/Correspondence
    - Anglican Church, 1981 Jun (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - re. Bi-regional projects/exchanges, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Campi, Emidio to Robert Mackie on his 80th birthday, 1979 Apr 13 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Campus Ministry, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Canadian Caucus Study Day, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - Canadian Caucus, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), 1987 (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - Church Relations Committee - Canada, 1978 Nov-1980 May, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Enns, Linda, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Episcopal Church Publishing, Co., 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - re. Federation Newsletter WSCF Journal, 1985 Oct -1986 Jun (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Friends Students, 1984-1987 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Great Peace Journey (materials from Ann-Cathrin Jarl), 1986 (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - Green Book Narratives, 1986 Jul (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - Human Rights - El Salvador, Korea, Philippines, 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - re. Deborah Huntington's proposed study, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 123)
    - Inter-Regional Office (IRO) Communiques, 1977-1980 (Box 7, Folder 124-126)
    - IRO and Officers, 1981-1986, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 127-129)
    - IRO announcement of the dissolution of the North America Regional Office, 1988 Jul (Box 7, Folder 129A)
    - Johnson, Peter (N.A. Regional Secretary), 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 130)
    - Johnson, Peter - Special Project Publication: Valliancourt, 1978 Oct 20 (Box 7, Folder 131)
    - re. John Jordan's dismissal from the United Methodist Church General Board of Global Ministries, 1986 Sep-Oct (Box 7, Folder 132)
    - Jubilee 1987 (Follow-up), 1988 Jan-Mar (Box 7, Folder 133)
    - re. Lochhead's The Liberation of the Bible, 1978 Jan, 1979 Jan-Aug (Box 7, Folder 134)
    - Lutheran Student Movement in Canada, 1978 Nov-1980 May (Box 7, Folder 135-136)